Finding Aid for the Civil War Collection, 1840-1929 (bulk 1861-1865)
Buffalo History Museum. Research Library
Civil War Collection, 1840-1929 (bulk 1861-1865)
Mss. C00-3
Buffalo History Museum. Research Library
5 boxes (2.5 linear feet)
Buffalo History Museum Research Library
Contains civil war period documents and materials reflective of the Western New York area.
Administrative Information
Terms of Access
The Civil War Collection, 1840-1929, is open for research.
Administrative Information
Acquisition Information
Specimens of Civil War envelopes; Thrasher, Thomas (The Hawks Book Store); gift; 1886/07/22; unknown
Confederate order book and memoranda of discharged soldiers Howe, Sallie Barry; gift; 1889/07/22; unknown
W.W. Potter reminiscences Bowden, Margaret; gift; 1912/03/00; unknown
Madison Buell scrapbook of recollections re: Civil War telegraphy; Buell, Lesley D.; unknown; 1932/09/29; unknown
John Ketchum collection of Civil War emblems Plimpton, Mrs.; unknown; 0000/00/00; unknown
L.L. Barney, pocket remembrances for 1863 Goering, G.E.; unknown; 0000/00/00; unknown
Accruals and Additions
No further accruals are expected to this collection.
Alternate Forms
W.W. Potter, "Three Years with the Army of the Potomac" (box 5, folder 9) available on microfilm (M88-1).
Historical Note
"Experts agree that it took a plentiful supply of the Four M's: Men, Money, Material, and Morale. Erie County, New York played a part if the victory by contributing its share of the 4 M's to the Union Cause."
-- Brown, R. C. (1973). Erie County and the Civil War. Adventures in Western New York History, v. 18. [Buffalo, N.Y.]: Buffalo History Museum. Available online.
Scope and Content Note
Muster rolls, histories, diaries and other official and personal papers concerning various New York regiments and naval operations, including the 3rd, 20th, 21st, 49th, 94th, 100th, ll6th and 179th Infantry; 11th and 12th Cavalry; 1st Light Artillery (Wiedrich's Battery), 12th Light Artillery, 27th Light Artillery (Eaton's Battery), and 16th Heavy Artillery, as well as some non-New York military units. Also included are passes used by Samuel Wilkeson for reporting for the New York Tribune, 1861; personal letters, 1840-1882; Confederate muster rolls and other records; documentation of war dead, particularly from Orleans County, New York.; muster and descriptive rolls of Erie County: W.T. Anderson collection of Civil War autographs, communications and maps; reminiscences by Madison Buell and W.W. Potter, M.D.; and other materials, including autographs, emblems, soldiers' ballots and excerpts from diaries and letters of Elizabeth Knowles.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in fourteen series:
I. New York Infantry Regiments
II. New York Cavalry Regiments
III. New York Artillery Regiments
IV. Sharpshooters and Mounted Rifles Units
V. Naval Activities
VI. Non-New York Military Regiments
VII. Samuel Wilkeson Papers
VIII. Personal Letters
IX. Confederate Manuscripts
X. Records of War Dead
XI. Muster and Descriptive Rolls for Erie County
XII. Reminiscences
XIII. W.A. Anderson Collection
XIV. Diary Excerpts, Autographs, Emblems, and Papers Concerning Unidentified Regiments.
I-IV arranged consecutively by regiment number.
Container List
- New York Infantry Regiments, 1861-1929, I.
  - 3rd Regiment - Company B (Excelsior or Sickles Brigade), circa 1860- 1861 (Box-folder 1.1)
    Muster - In Rolls: Company A (Captain Robert Gardner); Company C (Captain Jeremiah Washburn); Company D (Captain Win. Alberger); Company E (Captain James Strong); Company G (Captain Edward Lee); Company H (Captain Elisha Hayward); Company I (Captain Horace Thomas) Company K (Captain John Layton) add Field and Staff, May, 1861
    Muster - In Roll of Major Chester Sternberg, September, 1862; Provision Returns (Hospital): 21stRegiment from February 16-20; February 21-28; March 1-5; March 6-10; March 11-15; March 16-20; and March 21-25, 1863; Mustering - Out of Service of Lt. Colonel Chester Sternberg, May, 1863
    Muster - Out Rolls: Company A, Captain Levi Vallier (Late Captain Gardner's Company), Company C, Captain George Remington" (Late Captain Washburn's Company); Company D, Captain Byron Schermerhorn (Late Captain Alberger's Company); Company E, Captain Allen Adams (Late Captain Strong's Company); Company G, Captain Daniel Myers; Company H. Captain Peter Doyle (Late Captain Hayward's Company); Company I, Captain Robert Gardner; Company K, Captain John Layton and Field aud Staff, May, 1863
    Constitution of Veterans Club of 21st Regiment, N.Y.S. Volunteers [18__or early 1900's?]
    Plan for Re-organization Of Veterans Club of 21st Regiment, N.Y.S. Volunteers [18__ or early 1900's]?
    Civil War Pensioners: 21st Regiment, New York Infantry; also 33rd Infantry. Battery, New York Light Artillery, June, 1929 Records [Manuscript enclosed as miscellaneous material] Miscellaneous Folder
  - 20th Regiment, N.Y.S.M., 1863 (Box-folder 1.2)
    Muster - In Rolls [2years: Company F - 21st Regiment, Folder #2 Captain George Dewitt Clinton, April, May, 1861 [Manuscripts enclosed as miscellaneous material-some duplication]
    Various Returns or Reports of Captain George Clinton; May, June, July, October, December, 1861 and February and 1862 [Manuscript enclosed as miscellaneous material-some duplication]
    Invoices of Commissary Property turned George Clinton by Lt. Colonel Porter; February 15; March 29, 1863
    Invoices of Subsistence Stores turned over to, Clinton by Captain Doyle, February 15, 1863; by Captain February 16 and March 31, 1863; by Captain Doyle, February 23, March l, 3, 7, 14, 20, 28, 1863
    Acknowledgment of payment rec'd from Captain George Clinton by Non-Commissioned officers, musicians and privates from extra duty in Subsistence Department, November and December 1862, January, 1863 and February, 1863
    Acknowledgment of payment record from Captain George Clinton by privates for extra duty in Subsistence Department December, 1862 and January and February, 1863 and February, 1863
    Provisions Issued to Hospital (Dr. Fry, Surgeon), by Captain George Clinton, February 7 to February 28, 1863, March 1 to March 31, 1863
    Provisions issued to Volunteers by Captain Clinton, Folder #2 February 7 to February 28, 1863; March 1 to March 31, 1863 [copy] [Manuscripts enclosed as miscellaneous material] Disbursements by Captain Clinton to Nicholas Morris, et February and March, 1863, [Manuscripts enclosed as miscellaneous materiel] Summary Statement of Funds record, disbursed, and transferred by Captain George Clinton, February and March, 1863, [Manuscripts enclosed as miscellaneous material]
    Return of Provisions to Captain Doyle and Captain Benedict by Captain George Clinton, February and March, 1863 [copy] [Manuscripts enclosed as miscellaneous material]
    Provisions Issued to Hospital (Dr. Loughran, Surgeon) by Captain Clinton, March 1 to March 31, 1863 [Manuscript enclosed as miscellaneous material]
    Abstract Special Requisition by Captain Clinton (not approved), March 17, 1863 [Enclosure]
    Return of Subsistence Property by Captain Clinton Lieutenant Colonel A. P. Porter (Issued by Lieutenant Treligh and Bingham), March 31, 1863 [Manuscripts enclosed as miscellaneous material]
    Consolidated Abstract of Provisions Sold to Officers by Captain Clinton, March, 1863 [Manuscripts enclosed as miscellaneous material]
    Letter to Colonel Rogers from Captain Clinton, stating need for appointment of officer to Quarter Master Department, May, 1863 [Manuscripts enclosed as miscellaneous material]
    History of Company F: Its Organization and Changes since May, 1861; [1862] [Manuscripts enclosed as miscellaneous material]
    Allotment Roll. [186 ?]
    Muster - Out Roll - Captain Clinton, May, 1863 [Manuscripts enclosed as miscellaneous material]
  - 21st Regiment, N.Y.C., 1861-1929 (Box-folder 1.3)
    Muster - In Roll - Company B; Captain Henry Gaylord, May,1861
    Muster - Out Roll, Company. B; Captain Algar Wheeler [Late Captain Gaylord's Company]; May, 1863
    John Hayward Papers - Company B.; Donated, October, 1886 [Includes Chronicles of 21st Regiment.]
  - 21st Regiment- Company F, 1861-1929 (Box-folder 1.4)
    Soldier's Power of Attorney (October 12, 1864) and affidavit of absent voter, Brig. General Daniel D. Bidwell & 9 th Regiment, October 2, 1864
    Muster - Out Roll of Company D (Captain William Wheeler) of & 49th Regiment, October 31, [1864]?
    Proof of Death of Frank Motch of Company F, 49 th Regiment; also disregarding claim of Abigail Motch regarding pension, July 26, 1866
    Newspaper clippings regarding Services of 49th Regiment [no date] [Manuscript on reverse side].
  - 21st Regiment- Company F, 1861-1929 (Box-folder 1.5)
    Affidavits of absent voters (Soldiers) 116th William Husted (October 20, 1864 in duplicate); Orton Clark, October 21,1864
    Special Order #95: Private H. G. Emerson (116th Regiment) detached from Regiment to join Captain J. F. Ernst, Quarter Master Corps, November 24, 186h
    Request to Assistant. Adjutant General by Captain Ernst that Private H. G. Emerson, 116th Regiment., be retained in Quarter Master's Department as clerk, June 1, 1865
    Letter to Honorable Millard Fillmore of B.H.S. from Regiment. Members regarding disposition of 2nd Battle Flag (116th Regiment.) to B.H.S.; also History of Regiment. Flag, August 9, 1867
  - 21st Regiment- Company F, 1861-1929 (Box-folder 1.6-1.7)
  - 21st Regiment-Company B (Box-folder 1.8)
  - 21st Regiment-muster rolls (Box-folder 1.9)
  - 21st Regiment, John Hayward papers, 1863 (Box-folder 1.10)
  - 21st Regiment, N.Y. - miscellaneous (Box-folder 2.1)
    Application for Company Organization; Company H, 100th Folder #1 Regiment with list of names, July 25, 1861; Also Muster Roll from April 30, 1862 to June 30, 1862
    C. E. Walbridge to Colonel W. W, H. Davis accepting appointment as acting Brigade Quarter Master, January 7, 1862
    Morning Reports - April 12 and 19, 1862; August l, 12 and 30, 1862; December 10, 11, 24 and 29, 1863; January l, 1864, February 18, 1864; March 21, 186h and April l, 1864
    Reports of Field Officer of Day; Camp Scott May l, 1862; Gloucester Point, September 26 and October 26, and November 17, 1862
    Letter: Sergeant Leopold Evert to Brig. General H, M. Naglee regarding Court Martial trial, June 19, 1862
    List of Commissioned Officers, July 17, 1862 [Manuscript enclosed as miscellaneous material - duplication]
    Extract from Special Orders 247 - George B. Dandy, appointed Colonel of 100th New York Volunteers, ordered to join Regiment, August 29, 1862
    Provision Returns: October 7-10, 1862; March 1-10, March 1-31; March 21-31, 1863
    Communication to Capt. Johnston from Colonel G. B. Dandy, regarding prisoner, George Parks, October 27, 1862
    Request for Commissary Stores; November l, 4,?, 1862 and March,1863
    Letter to adjutant 104thRegiment. from Colonel Dandy, regarding volley of musketry November 6, 1862
    Charges of Leopold Evert against Private Robert Wiggins, November 17, 1862
    Reports: Best Shots by Guard 100 the Regiment. for week ending November 29, 1862 and December13, 1862
    Charges Preferred Against Lieutenant Newall, December 16 Folder#l or 17(?), 1862
    Report of Men on Extra Duty, December 26, 1862
    Report of Officers and Men Ready to march by Lieut, Colonel C. N. Otis, December, 1862
    General Order #24 - Trials and Sentences of Three Soldiers, January17, 1863
    General Order#6 - Appointment of Captain M. H. Tapping as Provost Marshall, January 24, 1863
    Returns of the l00thRegiment of Infantry, New York Volunteers; February, 1863; November, 1863; December, 1863 and February, l864
    Special Order #14; Lt. I. H. Dandy relieved from Court Martial Duty, March 13, 1863
    Appointment of General Court Martial for trial of Colonel. B. Dandy, September 14, 1863
    Roster of Commissioned Officers, November 24, 1863; January 1864 and February 1864
    Reports of Brigade Officer of Day (Headquarters, 2nd Brigade): November 28, 1863 Morris Island, January 4, 31; February. 9, March 20, 25, and 28, 1864
    100th Regiment on Folly Island - from Diaries of Private George N. Stoddard, 1863; [Extract from Special Order 13: Notice of Dismissal of E, L. Bishop for Absence without authority, January 9, 1864
    Inspection Report of Food For Soldiers, March 7, 18, 24, and 25, 1864; Soldiers Power of Attorney, October, 1864; and Affidavits absent voters (Soldiers), November, 1864
    Reunion and Dedication of Memorial to 100th New York Folder #1 Volunteer Infantry (Duplicate Copies), September 25, 1916
    Proceedings of 31st and 32nd Annual Reunions of 100th New York Veteran Association at Buffalo, August 16, 1917 and July 18, 1818 [Manuscripts enclosed as miscellaneous material]
    Letter from War Dept. Stating Military Records of Soldiers of 100th New York Veterans Association of Buffalo, September. 10, 1918 Enclosure]
    Colonel James Malcolm Brown Papers (100th Regiment commander)
    Papers of Captain C. Henshaw's Company K, 100th Regiment.
    Warren Granger Letterbook (Special Interest in 100th Regiment)
  - 21st Regiment, N.Y.V.-Diary of Charles E. Johnson (Box-folder 2.2)
    Substitutes Credited to Erie Company; also names of principles, November 1864
    Roll of Recruits and Substitutes of Erie Company, 1864
    Muster and Descriptive Roll of Substitutes Mustered into Service from November, 1864 to April, 1865
    Muster and Descriptive Roll of Substitutes, June 7, 1865
    Muster and Descriptive Roll of Enlistments for September and October, June 7, 1865
    Muster mud Descriptive Rolls of Volunteers - no date [Manuscript enclosed as miscellaneous material]
    Muster and Descriptive Rolls of Draftees, June 1865
    List of Persons Liable to Do Military Duty (Town of Brant), 1866
  - 49th Regiment, N.Y.V., 1864-1866 (Box-folder 2.3)
  - 94th Regiment, N.Y.V., 1864-1865 (Box-folder 2.4-2.6)
  - 100th Regiment, N.Y.V., 1861-1865 (Box-folder 3.1)
    Includes papers of Captain James Brown (General): Commander of Third Regiment, Company B (Excelsior or Sickles Brigade)
  - 100th Regiment, N.Y.V., 1861-1865 (Box-folder 3.2)
    Consolidated Provision Return for 20th Regiment, N.Y.S.M.; February 16-28; March 1-10; March 11-20; March 21, 31, 1863
    Special Requisition for 20th Regiment: (Lieutenant Freligh) February 17, 27 (2 copies), 1863; Also March 17, 1863 (not approved - in triplicate)
    Note regarding Hospital Fund (Captain Benedict) February 28, 1863
    Provision Return (Hospital): 20th Regiment; March 1-5, March 6-10, March 11-15, March 16-20, March 21-25, and March 26-31, 1863
  - 100th Regiment, N.Y.V., Veterans' reunions and memorials, 1915-1918 (Box-folder 3.3)
    Muster - In Roll of Captain Daniel Blackford, (179th Folder #3 Regiment.), May 16, 1864
    Muster Roll of Captain Daniel Blackford, (179 Regiment) June 30, 1864
    Muster Roll of Captain Louis Ottenst (179Regiment) August 31, 1864
  - 100th Regiment, N.Y.V., Colonel James Malcolm Brown papers, 1861-1862 (Box-folder 3.4)
    General Order #36: Farewell Address Of Colonel Adrian Root (94th Regiment) to 3rd Brigade of 2nd Division, 1st Army Corps, May 21, 1863
    Soldier's Power Of Attorney; affidavit of absent Soldier voters: Colonel Adrian Root, of 94th Regiment, Nov. l, 1864
    Muster -Out Rolls of Captain Orlo Mason (Company A);Captain Dexter Sears (Company B); Captain Chauncey Kilbarn (Company C); Captain Jos. Mollison (Company D); Captain Charles Parker (Company E); Captain Augustus Fields (Company F); Captain Walter Chester (Company G); Lieut, James Thomas (Company H); Captain C. V. Mesler (Company I); Captain Michael Leonard (Company K); Field and Staff, Colonel Adrian Root,, July, 1865
  - 100th Regiment, N.Y.V., Company K (Eagle Brigade) (Box-folder 3.5)
    Letter from Major E. Po Chapin of 44th Regiment, May, 1862 [Manuscript enclosed as miscellaneous materials
    Contribution to Ellsworth's Assn. of N.Y.S. to organize People's Regiment (44th) in honor of late Colonel Ellsworth, no date
    Provision Return (35th Regiment):February 7-28, 1863
    Signatures of Corporal Commanders, February 12, 1863 [Presented to B.H.S. by George Wright, Lt. 35th Regiment]
    Special Requisition for 35th Regiment - no date [duplicate Copy]
    Special Requisition for Lieutenant Bingham, 23rd Regiment, March 27, 1863
    Muster - Out Roll of Captain George Baker's Company D, 74th Regiment, August 3, 1863
    Payment claims due Mrs. John Dennison (husband war prisoner - 155th Regiment), October 11, 1864 [Manuscript enclosed as miscellaneous material]
    Proof of death of pensioner, Sarah Krein (husband in 33rd Regiment); no further interest in pension claim of guardian: County Clerks Office, May 21, 1866
    Letter to C. L. Dayton [from Enrolling Officer, Captain E. B. Miller, regarding delinquents in 98th Regiment, October 1866
  - 100th Regiment, N.Y.V., Diary of George N. Stoddard (Box-folder 3.6)
  - 100th Regiment, N.Y.V., Warren Granger letterbook (mainly concerning 100th Regiment) (Box-folder 3.7)
  - 116th Regiment, N.Y.V., 1864-1867 (Box-folder 3.8)
  - 179th Regiment, N.Y.,V., circa 1864 (Box-folder 3.9)
  - Other New York infantry regiments (11th, 23rd, 33rd, 35th, 44th, 74th, 98th, 155th) (Box-folder 3.10)
- New York Cavalry Regiments, 1864-1865, II.
  - 10th Regiment, Company C L.L. Barney, Daily Remembrance for 1863, (diary) (Box-folder 3.10A)
  - 11th Regiment (Samuel H. Wilkeson papers), 1864 (Box-folder 3.11)
  - 12th Regiment, 1865 (Box-folder 3.12)
  - Other New York Cavalry regiments (2nd, 5th, 16th) (Box-folder 3.13)
- Artillery Regiments, 1861-1908, III.
  - 1st Regiment Light Artillery - Battery I (Wiedrich's Battery), 1861-1889 (Box-folder 3.14)
  - 12th New York Independent Battery Light Artillery history, circa 1862-1908 (Box-folder 3.15)
  - 12th New York. Independent Battery Light Artillery - muster-out roll, 1865 (Box-folder 4.0)
  - 127th New York Independent Battery Light Artillery (Eaton's Battery) regimental histories, circa 1861-1908 (Box-folder 4.1)
    Supplies In Possession of Captain H. Hascall, Company I, 1st Regiment Artillery, August, 1861
    First Regiment Artillery (Light; Veteran) Muster - Roll' of Battery I (Captain Michael Wiedrick), October 16, 1861 [Manuscripts enclosed as miscellaneous material
    Letters to Brig. General A. V. Steinwehr from Captain Michael Wiedrick, regarding report of Battery's action: May 10 and July 1, 2, and 3 at Gettysburg, 1863 [Manuscripts en- " closed as miscellaneous material]
    Civil War Record of 2nd Lieutenant Jacob Schenkelberger, 1st Regiment, Battery I, Light Artillery (186_?)
    Subscription Lists of Contributors to Wiedrick's Battery Fund to enable veterans to attend dedication of monument at Gettysburg, April, 1889 [Manuscripts enclosed as miscellaneous material]
  - 127th New York Independent Battery Light Artillery, Journal of [John B. Eaton ?], January 1861-April 1865 (Box-folder 4.2)
    Morning Report Book of 27th New York Light Battery, 1862-1865
    John B. Eaton's History of 27th Battery (Captain Eaton in command) New York Light Artillery, April, 1888 [Manuscripts enclosed as miscellaneous material]
    Roster of Commissioned Officers of 27th Independent Battery of New York light Artillery prepared by Captain John B. Eaton, March, 1889; Muster - Out Roll of 12th Independent Battery Light Artillery - Captain Charles A. Clark, June, 1865; History of 12th New York Battery by Charles A. Clark - no date [All above material gift of Charles A. Clark, March, 1908]
    Letter to Mr. F. H. Severance of B.H.S. from Charles A. Clark (Lt. 27th Battery; Later Captain 12th Battery) regarding donation of material. March 18, 1908 [Enclosure]
  - 127th New York Independent Battery Light Artillery, Journal of [John B. Eaton ?], April 1865-May 1867 (Box-folder 4.3)
    Pass to Samuel Wilkeson from Secretary of War Cameron (August 1861) and General Winfield Scott (September 1861) [Manuscripts enclosed as miscellaneous material - duplication]
    Soldier's Power of Attorney and affidavit envelope for absent voters (Soldiers): Samuel H. Wilkeson, 11th Cavalry Regiment, October 1862 [Duplication of Manuscript]
    Members of New York Delegation in Congress request 10th New York Cavalry be mounted, April 24, 1862
    Special Order #25 to Colonel James Savage (12th New York Cavalry)defining duties of his troops Folder #3 in North Carolina, May 7, 1865 [Manuscript enclosed]
    Special Order #32 to Major R. Taylor (12th New York Cavalry) regarding information of Home Guard Organizations in Halifax and Northampton Counties (North Carolina) by order of Colonel James Savage, May 23, 1865
    Orders to Major R. M. Taylor (12th New York Cavalry) from Colonel James regarding duties in area under his command June 9, 1865
    Request from W. Holden to Major General Cox for ammunition for county police in Halifax and Northampton Counties, June 26, 1865
    Order to Muster out of service Major R. M. Taylor's command (12th New York Cavalry) also commendation for his services from Brig. General Thomas Heath, July 26, 1865
    Letter to President Andrew Johnson from Mayor William Fargo (Buffalo) regarding Major R. M. Taylor's request for clemency for soldiers, October 26, 1865
  - 16th New York Heavy Artillery regiment, 1865-1866 (Box-folder 4.4)
    First Regiment United States Sharpshooters: Special Order Folder #4 his command by Colonel Hiram Berdan 1861
- Sharpshooters and Mounted Rifle Units, 1861-1864, IV.
  - 2nd Regiment, New York Mounted Rifles, 1864 (Box-folder 4.5)
    Soldier's Power of Attorney: Absent voters (Sol-Folder #5 diets) - Jerry P. Fairman of 2nd Regiment of New York Mounted Rifles, October 15, 1864 [Manuscript enclosed as miscellaneous material - duplication]
  - 1st Regiment, United States Sharpshooters, 1861 (Box-folder 4.6)
    Letter written by Lt. Com. Budd, U.S.N., February 25, Folder #6 1862 [Enclosure]
    A. C. Stimer's Description of fight between Merrimac and Monitor; May 5, 1862 [Duplicate Manuscript and enclosures] Donated by Mr. Frank Blakeslee, June 27, 1877
    Copy of Lieutenant Commanders Perkin's Report regarding Action of Chickasaw, United States Ship at Battle of Mobile Bay, to Admiral Farragut, August 7, 1864
    Sailor's Absentee vote (Power of Attorney): Charles Fosdick, United States Ship. Samson, October 22, 1864
    Telegram from Major General Herron to Colonel W. H. Dickey, May 20, 1865
    Comments on Battle of Mobile Bay (Chickasaw, United States Ship) by Edmund S. Wheeler, U.S.N. co F. H. Gibbens, August 11, 1911 [Enclosures] Gift of Nelson S. Taylor, December 1941
    Description of United States Ship Chickasaw - undated
    Agreement between Continental Iron Works and Captain Erickson, et all, regarding Iron Battery Hall, undated
- Naval Activities, 1861-1911, V.
  - 1861-1911 (Box-folder 4.7)
  - Naval recruiting rosters (C.E. Young papers), 1864-1865 (Box-folder 4.8)
- Non-New York Military Regiments, 1861-1863, VI.
  - 1861-1863 (Box-folder 4.9)
- Samuel Wilkeson Papers 1861, VII.
  - Passes issued from War Department and Army for newspaper reporting, 1861 (Box-folder 4.10)
- Personal Letters 1840-1882, VIII.
  - circa 1840-1865 (includes letters of Carl Matteson) (Box-folder 4.11)
  - 1861-1865, 1882 and undated (Box-folder 4.12)
- Confederate Manuscripts, 1861-1865, IX.
  - Muster rolls, list of officers and Mississippi secession ordinance, 1861-1865 (Box-folder 5.1)
    Personal Letters (miscellaneous) 1840-1865
    Personal Letters, 1861-1864 [Gift of Mrs. L. Marvin,-Buffalo B.H.S.]
    Letters by Captain E. C. Parker, prisoner in Libby Prison. November 1863
    Carl Matteson's Letters, 1865-1865
  - Confederate order book and memoranda of discharged soldiers, 1861-1863, belonging to a Georgia regiment and captured in Sherman's "March to the Sea" (Box-folder 5.1A)
- Records of War Dead, 1861-1875, X.